<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Team, | Siyelo]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/blog/categories/team-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-03T16:59:32+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Siyelo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@siyelo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Focus Hocus Pocus]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/focus-hocus-pocus"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T12:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/focus-hocus-pocus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello <strong>Siyelo</strong>!</p>

<p>Today is my last day at work before heading into a new adventure. In order to skip all the resignation letter bullshit and because I received the enormous list of bugs you have been saving for me, I'll try to be very short.</p>

<p>After fixing all the bugs, I'll need to clean and leave the company laptop I work on too. So, I'll just try if the following command works well on Ubuntu 12.04. :) Random readers of this blog are not advised to try this at home!</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo rm -R /
</code></p>

<p>Now that we are done with all of that, it's time for some enjoyment.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/g4ouPGGLI6Q" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>All the best in future!</p>

<p>/<strong>dalibor</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's not you, it's me...]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/its-not-you-its-me"/>
    <updated>2012-10-05T15:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/its-not-you-its-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Part of a tradition (that we borrowed from our friends at World Wide Creative) is for everyone to write a light-hearted resignation note when they leave Siyelo. Here's the one from our resident Clojure expert, and Ping-Pong Chief, Peter Garbers;</p>

<p><a href="/images/old/2012/10/balls_of_fury.jpg"><img src="/images/old/2012/10/balls_of_fury.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><em>Dear Siyelo</em></p>

<p><em>The time has finally come for me to leave you. My time with the company has been something I will always remember. I have had much more fun than I would have ever thought and learnt a lot in the process. However, there are several reasons that have forced my decision.</em></p>

<p><em>The truth of the matter is that, I'm feeling rather inadequate around all the other members of the team:</em></p>

<p><em><strong>Glenn:</strong>Your knowledge of bad music is something I don't think that I will ever be able to compete with. (<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nNhNLi2oac8">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nNhNLi2oac8</a>). Need I say more?</em></p>

<p><em><strong>Sachin:</strong>I'm afraid I don't think I will ever be able to grow a beard like you. It's emasculating. What really irks me is that you refuse to embrace this gift bestowed upon you.</em></p>

<p><em><strong>Dalibor:</strong>I was the king of table tennis, or so I thought until you arrived earlier this year and smashed those dreams into little pieces.</em></p>

<p><em><strong>Dime:</strong>Your knowledge of metal music is far superior to mine. It hurts me to admit this so I won't expand on it further.</em></p>

<p><em><strong>Wendy:</strong>I'll never be as persistent as you. No, I haven't done timesheets for today.</em></p>

<p><em>Now, with our latest addition to the team, Nicole, I'm not even the prettiest person in the team!</em></p>

<p><em>I'll always treasure my time here and hope you enjoyed having me as much as I enjoyed being here.</em></p>

<p><em>Peter</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
