<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Design | Siyelo]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-19T01:42:47+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Siyelo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@siyelo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solving HTML5 compatibility issues]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/solving-html5-compatibility-issues"/>
    <updated>2010-08-25T14:24:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/solving-html5-compatibility-issues</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why use <code>&lt;div id="header"&gt;</code> when you can use just <code>&lt;header&gt;?</code> This is expecially convenient when you have tons of divs and becomes hard to trace everything. You get an extra level of visual code separation, but even more importantly you get a default hierarachy system that will give your code a common sense.</p>

<p>But enough about why HTML5 tags are awesome, and how about their acctual use in practise? As you might already know they are not really accepted by the current browsers, and won't be for some time. They are implementing more of the HTML5 and CSS3 magic as we speek, but it's a process that will take a while. So, what do we do about jumping on the HTML5 train?</p>

<p>The first solution is a very simple one and apllies to normal type of browsers like Firefox, Safari, Opera, Chrome: just put the CSS property <code>{ display: block; }</code> in your stylesheets:</p>

<p>``` css</p>



<p>```</p>

<p>and you're done. This converted them into block elements and returned them in the flow, so you can use the tags in your document.</p>

<p>But this is not so easy when it comes to Internet Explorer. You always need to put more effort into explaining something to a deaf, dumb and blind person, and so is this monstrocity spawned by Microsoft. What you need to do here is add some javascript, otherwise your html5 elements won't be recognized even by applying the block property. In the head of the document place this piece of code:</p>

<p>``` javascript</p>

<script>document.createElement('time');</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>This just created the <date> tag. You can use this method to create all the elements you require to make your html5-ish website acceptable for IE. There's also <a href="http://remysharp.com/downloads/html5.js">a script</a> made by Remy Sharp that will take care of this for you.</p>

<p>But nowdays we have more complete solutions to this problem, that also deal with cross-browser compatibility, improved css degradation and add some extra features. We have <a href="http://www.modernizr.com/">Modernizr</a> , JavaScript created by Faruk Ateş and Paul Irish that creates support for HTML5 and a lot of CSS3, and <a href="http://html5boilerplate.com/">Boilerplate</a> created by Paul Irish and Divya Manian, a cross-browser compatible and future-proof HTML template that support HTML5 and CSS3. What's really cool about Boilerplate is that they are working on a HAML/SASS port.</p>

<p>And for the end here are some cool examples of HTML5 websites, published recently by <a href="http://webdesignledger.com/inspiration/55-excellent-examples-of-websites-using-html5">WDL</a> . I know i'll be using HTML5 on my next website.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Web apps to outlast mobile/native apps]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/web-apps-to-outlast-mobilenative-apps"/>
    <updated>2010-06-25T15:29:08+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/web-apps-to-outlast-mobilenative-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/old/2010/06/pastedgraphic-7.png" alt="Pastedgraphic-7" /></p>

<p>Full presentation: <a href="http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Present-Future-Web-App-Design">http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Present-Future-Web-App-Design</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scalable full screen background image]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/scalable-full-screen-background-image"/>
    <updated>2010-04-28T09:52:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/scalable-full-screen-background-image</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I worked on a website for a <a href="http://freezing-light-25.heroku.com/">branding agency</a> that required a bit more avant-garde design with a large background image that could resize according to the browser’s window size and resolution. My research showed that most of the non-flash websites were done by JavaScript, but there was something else that caught my attention – a solution done with straight HTML, CSS and guess what – tables! Yeah, I know, the old arch-nemesis of web design. We almost started forgetting they existed, but they pop-up from time to time, reminding us of the good old days of poorly designed websites. And yet it was a solution so simple it’s almost creative and I was urged to try it out.</p>

<p>The whole trick is to create a single cell table, and apply few styles to make the magic work.</p>

<p>Note: I will use HAML and SASS for the code. Read here if you want to learn more about it: <a href="http://haml-lang.com/">http://haml-lang.com/</a>.</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:haml %}</p>

<h1>bg  </h1>

<p>  #bg_wrapper    </p>

<pre><code>%table{ :cellspacing =&gt; "0", :cellpadding =&gt; "0" }      
  %tbody        
    %tr          
      %td            
        %img#background{ :src =&gt; "images/index.jpg" }
</code></pre>

<p>{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>So it’s just a simple table with an image nested inside. Now the magic comes with combining CSS, or in this case SASS:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:sass %}
body
  width: 100%
  height: 100%
  overflow: hidden</p>

<h1>bg, table, td</h1>

<p>  #content
    width: 100%
    height: 100%
    overflow: hidden
  #bg_wrapper
    width: 200%
    left: -50%
    position: absolute
    top: -50%
    height: 200%
  td
    text-align: center
    vertical-align: middle
  #bg img
    margin: 0 auto
    min-height: 50%
    min-width: 50%
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>After this you can continue styling the rest of the page with straight CSS without worrying about the background. Leave the table as it is and nest the rest of your DIV’s straight in the body.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
