<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Agile | Siyelo]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/blog/categories/agile/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-30T17:17:26+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Siyelo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@siyelo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remote pair-programming with Screen]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/remote-pair-programming-with-screen"/>
    <updated>2011-11-03T10:37:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/remote-pair-programming-with-screen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Siyelo we have 2 distributed teams, one in Cape Town and another one in Skopje. Naturally, we had to figure out how to do remote pair programming between the two offices. There are different available options for remote pair-programming (a great summary post available <a href="http://evan.tiggerpalace.com/articles/2011/10/17/some-people-call-me-the-remote-pairing-guy-/">here</a>).</p>

<p>In the past, we often used Skype for screen sharing, but the problems with Skype are:</p>

<ul>
<li>you don't have control over the other screen</li>
<li>you cannot have both screen sharing and video</li>
<li>bandwidth of the internet connection sometimes can be a problem</li>
<li>it's not a tool for pair programming</li>
</ul>


<p>Recently we have been experimenting with Google+ hangouts and although it has the same limitations, we prefer it over Skype for audio/video communication. But, what we really want from a remote pair-programming tool is the ability to do real time code collaboration.</p>

<p>The solution: <a href="http://www.gnu.org/s/screen/">screen</a>. Screen can have many useful scenarios, but here I will focus on following two:</p>

<ul>
<li>read only - useful as a screen sharing tool by hosting read only screen session</li>
<li>permissive - useful as a real time code collaboration tool</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is how to setup screen for both scenarios. Note: A downside of a tool like Screen is that everyone needs to learn an editor that runs in terminal. Luckily we all like vim.</p>

<p>First we need to install SSH server because all communication will happen over secure channel:</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get install ssh
</code></p>

<p>For the read only scenario, we need to setup guest user account on the host machine. For security reasons we will create a read-only account with <a href="http://man.he.net/man1/rbash">rbash</a> (<a href="http://www.cyberciti.biz/faq/restrict-linux-users-to-their-home-directories-only/">restricted</a> bash) shell which will be used by the programmer we want to pair with to ssh into the host  machine we control and join the screen session.</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo useradd -s /bin/rbash guest
sudo passwd guest
sudo mkdir /home/guest
</code></p>

<p>Next we need to setup the guest shell.profile. Add the following to /home/guest/.profile</p>

<p><code>bash
trap "" 2 3 19 # stop user getting to shell
clear
echo "Welcome to pair-programming session"
echo -n "Press Enter to continue..." &amp;&amp; read
screen -x dalibor/pairprog
exit
</code></p>

<p>Here as you can notice "screen -x dalibor/pairprog" automatically will join the session named "pairprog" that is started by "dalibor" user on "guest" user login.</p>

<p>Next we need to install screen on the host machine (if it's not already installed).</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo apt-get install screen
</code></p>

<p>For security reasons, screen by default is installed so that other users within the system can not attach to screen session (error you will get is: "Must run suid root for multiuser support."). To allow multi user setup you need to execute following (you might need to change the path if screen is installed in /usr/bin/screen for example):</p>

<p><code>bash
sudo chmod +s /usr/bin/screen
sudo chmod 755 /var/run/screen
</code></p>

<p>Then you need to add the following screen config in ~/.screenrc file</p>

<p>``` bash
hardstatus on
hardstatus alwayslastline
startup_message off
termcapinfo xterm ti@:te@
hardstatus string "%{= kG}%-w%{.rW}%n %t%{-}%+w %=%{..G} %H %{..Y} %m/%d %C%a "
screen -t bash1 1</p>

<h1>multiuser setup</h1>

<p>multiuser on
aclchg guest -wx "#,?"
aclchg guest +x "colon,wall,detach"
```</p>

<p>Most important lines are "multiuser on" which allows multiuser access in the screen session and "aclchg" command which removes all write and execute permissions for all windows (#) and all commands (?) for user guest. With this setup, host can do anything and guest can just watch the screen or message by using Ctrl-a: wall "hi there".</p>

<p>Finally, communication goes like this: screen session is started by host with:</p>

<p><code>bash
screen -S pairprog
</code></p>

<p>Guest SSH to the host machine and automatically joins the screen session:</p>

<p><code>bash
ssh guest@host
</code></p>

<p>Then they can interact in the same terminal. More on the screen commands <a href="http://aperiodic.net/screen/multiuser">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you trust the user you can add full permission with "acladd"  command, and usually it's to be done on a shared server. Say we have user1 and  user2 logged in on shared server via SSH, user1 has added user2 in  the ~/.screenrc file.</p>

<p><code>bash
multiuser on
acladd user2
</code></p>

<p>And is starting pairprog screen session with:</p>

<p><code>bash
screen -S pairprog
</code></p>

<p>Then user2 can join that session with:</p>

<p><code>bash
screen -x user1/pairprog
</code></p>

<p>More info on screen command here in this <a href="http://aperiodic.net/screen/quick_reference">screen reference</a>. Basic commands are:</p>

<p><code>bash
Ctrl-a d # detach screen window
Ctrl-a Ctrl-a # flip-flop between two windows
screen -r # re-attach screen window
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are Agile Projects Doomed to Half-Baked Design?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/are-agile-projects-doomed-to-half-baked-design"/>
    <updated>2010-01-10T22:23:08+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/are-agile-projects-doomed-to-half-baked-design</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The answer is no.</p>

<p>An <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/theinfonaut/are-agile-projects-doomed-to-halfbaked-design">excellent presentation</a> from Alex &amp; Leslie from PivotalLabs and GetSatisfaction respectively tells why:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/39852" width="427" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p> <div style="margin-bottom:5px"> <strong> <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/theinfonaut/are-agile-projects-doomed-to-halfbaked-design" title="Are Agile Projects Doomed to Half-Baked Design?" target="_blank">Are Agile Projects Doomed to Half-Baked Design?</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/theinfonaut" target="_blank">theinfonaut</a></strong> </div></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Agile Contracts - Working group]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/agile-contracts-working-group"/>
    <updated>2009-11-04T11:09:04+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/agile-contracts-working-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.coactivate.org/projects/agile-contracts/">The Agile Contracts working group</a> has an excellent sample (<a href="http://www.coactivate.org/projects/agile-contracts/sample-fixed-price-agile-contract">fixed-price</a>) contract for a project delivery using SCRUM.</p>

<p>From memory it was posted by Jeff Sutherland and is from an actual project, so its fairly comprehensive.</p>

<p>(Note these are only samples and you should always seek legal advice before using 3rd-party contracts.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
