<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coderetreat | Siyelo]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/blog/categories/coderetreat/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-19T11:23:16+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Siyelo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@siyelo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Global Day Of Coderetreat 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/global-day-of-coderetreat-2012"/>
    <updated>2012-12-05T09:32:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/global-day-of-coderetreat-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/coderetreat_skopje_2012.png" alt="Global Day Of Coderetreat 2012 in Skopje (Macedonia)" /></p>

<p><a href="http://coderetreat.org">Coderetreat</a> is a day-long, intensive practice event focusing on the fundamentals of software development and design. By providing developers the opportunity to take part in focused practice, away from the pressures of 'getting things done', the coderetreat format has proven itself to be a fun and highly effective means of skill improvement.</p>

<p>While on a Coderetreat the participants try to improve their craft by learning from each other, focusing on fundamental design principles (such as the Simple Rules of Design and the SOLID principles) and by challenging many of their every day assumptions.</p>

<p>On December 8th, Coderetreats will be held all over the world as part of the <a href="http://globalday.coderetreat.org">Global Day of Coderetreat</a>. The Global Day of Coderetreat helps to raise awareness of Coderetreats and brings people together from all over the world. Most importantly, The Global Day of Coderetreat helps to support global efforts to find, encourage, and educate the next generation of software developers.</p>

<p>Last year, 94 cities participated. This year, it is expected approximately 200 cities to participate with an average of 15-20 participants per city.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
