<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: git | Siyelo]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/blog/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-03T15:37:36+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Siyelo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@siyelo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thou shalt clean thy branches: git rebase]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/thou-shalt-clean-thy-branches-git-rebase"/>
    <updated>2013-01-15T10:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/thou-shalt-clean-thy-branches-git-rebase</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I often find myself wondering when to do a interactive rebase (<code>git rebase</code>) vs a squashed merge (<code>git merge --squash</code>). The answer is rather subtle and can be found <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2427238/in-git-what-is-the-difference-between-merge-squash-and-rebase">here</a>. Essentially it comes down to whether you want to continue on the branch (interactive rebase) vs merge it now (merge squash).</p>

<p>Either way, you are rewriting histories, so you have to know what you're
doing.</p>

<p>A google search of ('git merge squash vs rebase') turns up <a href="http://paul.stadig.name/2010/12/thou-shalt-not-lie-git-rebase-ammend.html">this article from Paul Stadig</a> which rather irks me. Paul's stance in this article is that you should
'never' use git rebase/amend/squash. But these are all perfectly valid, and necessary parts of a healthly git workflow.</p>

<p>Interactive rebasing and merge squashing are essential if you care about having a <em>clean</em> git
history.  Linus explains it perfectly <a href="http://lwn.net/Articles/328438/">here</a></p>

<blockquote><p>You should rebase your <em>private</em> trees (thats a cleanup) (and never
 pull into a branch that isn't already in good shape)</p>

<p>You must never EVER destroy other peoples history</p>

<p>Keep your own history readable and dont expose your crap</p>

<p>Never pull into a branch that isn't already in good shape</p></blockquote>

<p>Stick to these simple rules, and rebase/squash as you please!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
