<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Weekly | Siyelo]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/blog/categories/weekly/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-07T14:00:30+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Siyelo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@siyelo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TL;DR: D3, Refactoring ActveRecord models & Templates for consulting engagements]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-8"/>
    <updated>2012-12-07T13:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's that time again... Friday and we all know that means Dev Chat. This week we had an insightful and abundant sharing of links.</p>

<p>Dime shared Data Driven Documents, <a href="http://d3js.org/">D3.js</a> is a JavaScript library for manipulating documents based on data.</p>

<p>Dalibor found the following articles <a href="http://blog.codeclimate.com/blog/2012/10/17/7-ways-to-decompose-fat-activerecord-models/">7 Patterns to Refactor  at ActiveRecord</a> Models and Demeter: It's not just a good idea. It's the law, very insightful as well as sharing <a href="http://www.sdruby.org/podcast/94">Refactoring ActiveRecord</a> Models podcast as Ben Hughes explores several techniques for refactoring models and preventing them from getting out of hand. Purchase <a href="http://railsantipatterns.com/">Rails AntiPatterns: Best Practice Ruby on Rails Refactoring</a> on amazon and learn how to identify and fix over 300 of the most common mistakes made in Ruby on Rails applications.</p>

<p>Glenn suggested reading about <a href="http://blog.obiefernandez.com/content/2008/09/master-services-agreement-part-1.html">Obie Fernandez's great MSA and SoW templates for consulting engagements</a>. Sachin shared project management theory <a href="https://aidylewis.heroku.com/2012/11/18/kanban-no-it-cant/">Kanban</a> and <a href="http://blog.headius.com/2012/11/refining-ruby.html">Refining Ruby</a>.</p>

<p>Last but not least Ile shared Know your gems and create <a href="http://robots.thoughtbot.com/post/35717411108/a-healthy-bundle">A Healthy Bundle</a> and <a href="http://blog.steveklabnik.com/posts/2012-11-22-introducing-the-rails-api-project">Introducing the Rails API Project
</a></p>

<p>Enjoy your weekend!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TL;DR: Rails 4, a responsive cat & a free book]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-7"/>
    <updated>2012-11-16T17:09:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With 42 Days left in 2012 until the Mayan Apocalypse and the world comes to an END we’ve decided to to share as much of our insight as possible!... Happy friday from Siyelo.</p>

<p>If you love freebies check this out. Dalibor received a free "<a href="http://https://twitter.com/sandimetz/status/268753825916133376">Practical Object-Oriented Design in Ruby</a>" book thanks to Sandi Metz and InformIT.  Great customer service!</p>

<p>Dali has been fully emerged in the <a href="http://blog.wyeworks.com/2012/11/13/rails-4-compilation-links/">Rails 4 compilation links</a>, a curated list of intersting links about the next release of Rails.  It's got pull requests, issues, commits, examples, posts, videos and much more.</p>

<p>Sachin spent way too much time playing with the <a href="http://roxik.com/cat/">Responsive cat</a>.  You may not have heard the term  <a href="http://kkovacs.eu/the-death-star-design-pattern">'The Death Star design pattern'</a> before but we're sure you've come across it.  Finally, Sachin shared an article about <a href="http://tx.pignata.com/2012/11/being-for-the-benefit-of-future-developer.html">being for the benefit of future developer</a> - an interesting read with tips about what you can do to look after the next person that'll working on your code.</p>

<p>Glenn shared an article on <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/how-startups-are-killing-off-bosses-2012-10">How Startups Are Killing Off Bosses</a>. Dime recommended downloading <a href="http://fitvidsjs.com/">Responsive videos</a>, A lightweight, easy-to-use jQuery plugin for fluid width video embeds and <a href="http://fortawesome.github.com/Font-Awesome">Font Awesome</a> an iconic font designed for use with Twitter Bootstrap.</p>

<p>Ile found <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aBgnlBoIkVM">10 things you didn't know you could do with Ruby</a> while watching cat videos on YouTube.  He also spent some time learning about things <a href="http://www.igvita.com/2012/11/14/wait-chrome-devtools-could-do-that/">you didn't know you could do with Chrome dev tools</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TL;DR: Learning Pyramids, Ruby 2.0 and Drunken User Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-6"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T15:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have had quite a informative week according to our Dev chat sessions, we combined last week's links with this week to give you quite a bit to cover.</p>

<p>Dali shared a few great articles with us this week:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://blog.8thlight.com/uncle-bob/2012/09/06/I-am-Your-New-CTO.html">New CTO</a> by Uncle Bob is an interesting read about how rational expectations from a new CTO may not always appear that way...until you look closely.</li>
<li><a href="http://blog.8thlight.com/paul-pagel/2011/12/16/fixed-feature.html">Fixed Feature</a> - an Agile method of fixed bid compensation where clients only pay for the product they receive.</li>
<li>The <a href="http://homepages.gold.ac.uk/polovina/learnpyramid/index.html">Learning Pyramid</a> diagram illustrates how much better teaching or doing is for retention of new information.</li>
</ul>


<p>It’s all too easy to give bad advice these days, Sachin recommends reading <a href="https://blog.intercom.io/asking-questions-versus-giving-advice/">asking questions versus giving advice</a>.</p>

<p>Our newest addition Ile shared <a href="http://http://www.netmagazine.com/shop/magazines/december-2012-235">Killer features that are coming in Ruby 2.0.</a>.</p>

<p>Dime introduced “<a href="http://www.netmagazine.com/shop/magazines/december-2012-235">how to achieve a more dynamic workflow</a>”, a Q&amp;A on <a href="http://uxdesign.smashingmagazine.com/2012/11/08/ux-design-qa-with-christian-holst/">Adaptive VS Responsive design</a> and lastly <a href="http://css-tricks.com/off-canvas-menu-with-css-target/">Off Canvas menu</a> layouts.</p>

<p>Finally, we think 3Sheets may have just discovered the future of User Testing:</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/4cMVKW-fR1M?feature=player_detailpage" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Enjoy your weekend!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TL;DR: Making Rails fast, Practical OO & Google data centers]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-5"/>
    <updated>2012-10-19T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dalibor has been reading up on how to boost the performance of Rails apps (hat tip to <a href="http://www.twitter.com/railsonfire">@railsonfire</a>):</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://blog.railsonfire.com/2012/05/06/Unicorn-on-Heroku.html">How to get 4x the performance out of Heroku with Unicorn</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.railsonfire.com/2012/05/18/Assets-Sprites-CDN.html">Make your website super fast with Asset Pipeline, Sprites &amp; Cloudfront</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Glenn's been checking out Flask as a Python alternative to Ruby's Sinatra; <a href="https://twitter.com/maximebf">@maxinebf</a> have a great <a href="http://maximebf.com/blog/2012/10/building-websites-in-python-with-flask/#.UIE8sGmwUqt">tutorial</a> on the topic.  </p>

<p>If you haven't already seen it, Sachin recommends watching <a href="https://twitter.com/sandimetz">@sandimetz</a> 's <a href="http://www.confreaks.com/videos/1115-gogaruco2012-go-ahead-make-a-mess">excellent presentation</a> at GoGaRuCo with practical examples of how OO design can help you manage your mess</p>

<p>Finally, one of Google's data centers has street view...and <a href="https://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;ll=35.898176,-81.548166&amp;spn=0.007622,0.013486&amp;sll=35.900197,-81.547024&amp;layer=c&amp;cid=7373938251588581469&amp;panoid=qlcZPzXMS12y_CrDh64Qvw&amp;cbp=13,339.35,,0,4.29&amp;gl=US&amp;t=m&amp;cbll=35.898186,-81.548184&amp;z=17">odd security</a> ...</p>

<p>Enjoy your weekend!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TL;DR: Great RSpect tests, TripAdvisors growth & Going password-less]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-4"/>
    <updated>2012-10-12T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/weekly-roundup-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another week has hurried by leaving us with exactly 80 days left to the end of 2012! Here's this week's edition of the Dev Chat round-up - let us know if you have any articles that you think we missed over the last 7 days.</p>

<p>Sachin and Glenn shared some tips &amp; tricks:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.igvita.com/slides/2012/devtools-tips-and-tricks/#1">Chrome dev tools</a> - a great primer to getting the most out of Chrome as a developer;</li>
<li><a href="http://betterspecs.org/">How to create a great RSpec test suite</a> - a simple and easy guide to whipping your tests into shape.</li>
</ul>


<p>Sachin also shared an article about the <a href="http://blogs.hbr.org/cs/2012/10/the_secrets_to_tripadvisors_im.html">secrets to TripAdvisors impressive growth</a> (warning: not related to scaling their site but an interesting read none the less).</p>

<p>Dalibor was looking at different ways of eliminating the need to store user passwords on your site:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/alsmola/nopassword">No Password</a> - a Rails gem that uses the 'Forgot Password' email token functionality to give you authentication without passwords. </li>
<li><a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2012/09/first-beta-release-of-mozilla-persona-login-without-passwords/">Mozilla Persona</a> - an authentication alternative to OpenID or Facebook Connect, with a focus on privacy and browser integration.</li>
</ul>


<p>And to end off, Peter shared <a href="http://www.futilitycloset.com/2012/09/25/the-copernicus-method/">"The Copernicus Method"</a>, which is a strangely accurate way of estimating the longevity of all sorts of things.</p>

<p>Have a great weekend!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
