<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: team | Siyelo]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/blog/categories/team/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-08T16:56:53+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Siyelo]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[support@siyelo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcoming Ile - Our newest team member]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.siyelo.com/welcoming-ile"/>
    <updated>2012-11-02T15:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.siyelo.com/welcoming-ile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're very proud to announce the newest addition to the Siyelo team - Ile Eftimov. Ile is a recent computer science graduate who is crossing over from PHP to the wonderful world of Ruby and Rails. We did a brief Q and A with Ile.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/ile.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>How would you describe yourself?</strong></p>

<p>"I would describe myself as a friendly, funny and chubby guy (although I've lost a few kilos in the last few months) :)"</p>

<p><strong>What interests you about Rails?</strong></p>

<p>"I really like open source and its philosophy. So PHP was my getaway drug to open source. After attending a local meetup about Ruby, I got in touch with Dalibor and he showed me the beauty of Rails. I really like the Rails community, it has a lot of great resources to learn. Also, I like the way the software is done (methodologies, Agile, XP, Kanban etc) and I like testing, which is a new thing for me."</p>

<p><strong>How have you found working at Siyelo so far?</strong></p>

<p>"I really like it here (at Siyelo). Everybody is friendly &amp; there are really nice and constructive discussions. I have learned a lot in the past 2 weeks and I am looking forward to learning more."</p>

<p><strong>Tell us a 'Yo mama' joke</strong></p>

<p>"Yo mama is so fat she wears a belt from the brand 'Equator'!"</p>

<p><strong>Are you willing to grow a moustache for Movember?</strong></p>

<p>"I would, if I could :("</p>

<p>We are really excited to have Ile on the team and we watch him develop as a Rails developer in the coming months.</p>

<p>Got a question for Ile? Ask him in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
